Part Four: Local Rinses for
Pain Control in the Mouth
Sometimes the mucositis worsens
in the mouth, causing you pain.
In that case, we can use two specific
rinses to help decrease the pain
locally in the mouth without causing you
any systemic side effects.
These are medications
that you can rinse and spit out.
Doxepin Mouth Rinse
Take the doxepin as prescribed
and mix 1 to 1 with water.
Take 2.5ml of doxepin
and mix with 2.5ml of water.
This will be a total of five milliliters.
Rinse for 30 seconds and then spit out.
Morphine Mouth Rinse
Take 5 to 10ml of morphine.
Dilute 1 to 1 with water
and swish and spit out the medication.
Both of these will require prescriptions
from your doctor.
So please be sure to check with your doctor
and ask if a prescription is right for you.
If pain still persists after all attempts to help mucositis-
baking soda/MuGard rinse,
lidocaine rinse and swallow,
and doxepin/morphine rinse and spit-
please watch the pain management videos.